<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Seabrookes caueat: or His warning piece to all his louing country-men, to beware how they meddle with the eyes In which is contayned the exact and most certaine remedies for all manner of infirmities, which shall happen vnto the eyes. Written for the generall good of this whole monarchie of great Brittaine. By Richard Seabrooke, practicioner in the art of the occulist.</title>
            <author>Seabrooke, Richard, b. ca. 1548.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11834</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22133</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101949</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837752</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837752</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2092</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11834)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2092)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1034:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Seabrookes caueat: or His warning piece to all his louing country-men, to beware how they meddle with the eyes In which is contayned the exact and most certaine remedies for all manner of infirmities, which shall happen vnto the eyes. Written for the generall good of this whole monarchie of great Brittaine. By Richard Seabrooke, practicioner in the art of the occulist.</title>
                  <author>Seabrooke, Richard, b. ca. 1548.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[62] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw. All-de, dwelling neere Christes Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D (-D8).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Eye --  Diseases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2092:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2092:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SEABROOKES CAVEAT: <hi>Or</hi> His warning piece to all his louing Country-men, to beware how they meddle with the Eyes. <hi>In which is contayned the exact and moſt certaine remedies for all manner of infirmities, which ſhall happen vnto the Eyes.</hi> Written for the generall good of this whole Monarchie of great <hi>BRITTAINE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By RICHARD SEABROOKE, Practicio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the Art of the Occuliſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Edw. All-de,</hi> dwelling neere Chriſtes Church. 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2092:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2092:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right noble and moſt vertuous Ladyes (being the Nurſing-Mothers, and Comforters of many poore-afflicted people) The <hi>Lady</hi> SYDNEY <hi>of</hi> Walſingham, <hi>and the Lady</hi> STRAVNGE, <hi>wife to the Honourable Knight, Sir</hi> HAMON STRAVNGE <hi>of</hi> Hunſton; RICHARD SEABROOKE <hi>wiſheth the encreaſe of Gods good bleſſings in this life, and all graces leading to life eternall.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt noble and vertuous Ladies,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I called to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the moſt iuſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of that euill ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant in the Goſpell, who buried his one Talent: It did quicken my conſcience and ſtirre vp my minde on the contrary, ere death ſhould preuent mee (according to that meaſure of knowledge in my profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wherewith God hath endued mee) to communicate with my deareſt Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb facs="tcp:2092:3"/>
my skill (ſuch as it is) by publiſhing in this ſmall Treatiſe the principall obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations of my whole practiſe. True it is, I haue now attained to the age of ſeauenty and two yeares, being from my youth by profeſſion an <hi>Occulist.</hi> In which courſe of life, as (to my great reioycing in the Lord, through his bleſſings vpon mine endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours) I haue helped very many (who haue beene long darkned) to their perfect ſight, ſo haue I ſeene by lamentable experience, not a few poore Chriſtians, of both ſexes, and all ages, by ſiniſter meanes and appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations made helpleſſe, and vtterly depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the moſt deare and delightfull light of their eyes. The originall of theſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes are ſometimes to be imputed to the negligence of Mothers and Nurſes: But for the moſt part, the Practicioners in this kinde are to be taxed, and of them alſo the negligent, the vnskilfull, and the wilfull, moſt of them more, ſtudious to lighten the purſes, rather then the paines of their grieued patients. All theſe ſorts (after my plaine manner) I haue briefely touched in certaine caueats: then I ſhew the cauſes of Blindneſſe, the ſeuerall hurtfull humours incident to the eyes, their qualities, and how to iudge which be curable and which incurable: and laſtly, I haue annexed the moſt approoued medicines and remedies which I haue found by long experience to be moſt profitable.</p>
            <p>I fore-ſee (moſt vertuous Madames) that
<pb facs="tcp:2092:3"/>
theſe aduertiſements comming from my ſelfe a plaine olde man; ſhall not eſcape the detractions and ſcoffes of proud and malicious cenſurers; but hauing for the warrant of my doings the teſtimonie of a good conſcience (that I haue ſincerely, charitably, and vpon knowne grounds pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded herein) I caſt behinde mee all the vniuſt aſpertions they poſſibly can throw vpon my name, I am a poore man my ſelfe, and my poore mite I freely caſt into the poore mans treaſury, wiſhing all them that are ſo humbly minded, not to deſpiſe what they not vnderſtand: But firſt to make tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, then to truſt, and ſo to take in good part that which is tendred vnto their good. And very ſure I am that I cannot want good atteſtation of my cures performed by theſe meanes; and thankfull acknowledgement alſo from ſuch as (vnder God) haue found helpe by mine applications.</p>
            <p>Now the reaſons enducing me (moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Ladies) to preſent this my ſimple labour to your excellent ſelues, are the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous reports of your noble vertues, whoſe charity, and piety, like two goodly col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbs, ſupport and hold vp a world of poore diſtreſſed people, which otherwiſe would periſh and fall to duſt in the ruines of their afflictions and affirmities, as alſo that I know the excellencie of your clement na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, will vouchſafe to accept a ſmall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, being offered of great good will and affection: In which ſince I can finde no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt,
<pb facs="tcp:2092:4"/>
becauſe your goodneſſe is my war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. I humbly craue pardon for my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and vowe euer till this little ſand of my life be conſumed, to remaine, The euer obliged ſeruant and true admirer of your vertues;</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>RICH. SEABROOKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2092:4"/>
            <head>To the courteous and indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Reader, eſpecially to all ſuch who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> troubled with any diſeaſe incident to the eyes.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Haue not here (courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and indifferent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) entertained thee with fine phraſes, and artificiall method (things curious and becomming the curious) I leaue that to thoſe which are more ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of priuate fame, then ſtudious for the common good. But I haue truly and plainely ſhewed thee how to beware of, and preuent certaine grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous inconueniences: where the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is curable, I haue ſet downe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued remedies for it, where it is incurable, I aduiſe thee to comfort
<pb facs="tcp:2092:5"/>
thy ſelfe in God, and ſaue thy money: Reade and practiſe, and as thou find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt any profit, take in good part my paines, but giue the whole praiſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, to whoſe holy protection I commit thee and my ſelfe, and all the faithfull in Christ Ieſus. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:2092:5"/>
            <head>CHAP. 1. <hi>Of Blindneſſe both curable and incurable in Infants, the cauſe, preuention, and cure.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, becauſe experience is the Mother and chiefe Nurſe of all wiſedome, and that by it we are led and conducted to the end of perfection, I will in this my ſmall Treatiſe take her by the hand, and as ſhee ſhall with the aſſiſtance of truth guide me, ſo both begin and finiſh this profitable labour which I hope ſhall be both to the glory of my God, and the generall profit of my deareſt belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Country.</p>
            <p>Know then all to whom this (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt inſupportable) infirmitie of Blindneſſe is burdenous and heauie,
<pb facs="tcp:2092:6"/>
that it hath two great and eminent enemies, Ignorance and Negligence, and by them it is often made deſperate and cureleſſe, which otherwiſe would either not be at all, or if hapning, yet reſt within the eaſieſt compaſſe of ſpeedy cure and preuention.</p>
            <p>To you Mothers then and Nurſes <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (for you are the firſt caretakers of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren) I direct my firſt admonitions, becauſe from you (when you prooue the leaſt remiſſe and careleſſe) doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede the greateſt errors, let mee ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly perſwade you by all meanes to beware of ſuffering your children to take colde in any part, eſpecially on their heads by ſitting with them long bare-headed, whether by the fire, in the Sunne, or in the open ayre, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally whilſt they are in their ſwadling cloathes, or in the tender time of their Infancie; a fault much too common amongſt Nurſes, and a negligence ſo offenſiue; that the defect of blindneſſe comming therby, the diſeaſe is hardly
<pb facs="tcp:2092:6"/>
or neuer to be cured: For the mould of the head not being then cloſed, the leaſt offence of colde ſtriking the braine, bringeth ſodaine and preſent blindneſſe, which defect found, ere the cauſe be diſcerned, Ignorance pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently giues out, that ſuch children were borne blinde: But I affirme it is nothing ſo, and for proofe thereof call to witneſſe mine experience, which I will ſhew in a few inſtances.</p>
            <p>Firſt, being in a place where my practiſe was knowne, there came to mee two women, within very fewe houres the one of the other, and brought to me two very ſweet Babes, one nineteene weekes olde, the other one and twenty, both which had very cleare and faire eyes, in all outward ſemblance, but abſolutely ſo blinde, that no blindneſſe could be greater: Then I tolde the Mother of the firſt childe, that queſtionleſſe in mine opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion her childe had taken colde whilſt it was in the ſwadling-cloathes, to
<pb facs="tcp:2092:7"/>
which the Mother made preſent an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that I had ſpoken truth, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that her Nurſe (within fiue or ſixe dayes after her deliuerance) had ſate by the fire with the childe bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed ſo long a time, that ſhee tooke offence thereat, and making her dreſſe vp the childe, the very next day after ſhe found that her childe was blinde, which ſhe was moſt certaine had ſeene very perfectly before.</p>
            <p>Then came the other woman with her childe, and I ſaid to her as to the firſt, and ſhee likewiſe conſented with mine opinion, and onely affirmed, that ſhe was aſſured her childe did ſee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly a moneth or fiue weekes after it was borne.</p>
            <p>Not long after this there came vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me (and one M. <hi>Surfleet,</hi> a very skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Occuliſt)</hi> another woman with a childe in the ſame manner, which child was not aboue foureteene weeks olde, and both our opinions were (as of the former) that colde was the only
<pb facs="tcp:2092:7"/>
cauſe of the diſeaſe, and ſhee agreed with vs ſhewing circumſtance, to leade her thereto; and onely affirmed that of her certaine knowledge her childe did ſee perfectly eight or nine dayes after it was borne.</p>
            <p>Now it was M. <hi>Surfleets</hi> abſolute opinion, that in theſe caſes there was no cure in Art: but for mine owne part I a little diſſent therein, and doe allow all vertuous induſtry to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied; becauſe it cannot bring the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe to a worſe end then it is already arriued, and may by Gods bleſſing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call that ſtrength and vigour to the member offended, which may reſtore that which was but a little put by, not vtterly forſaken; whereas to ceaſe from all manner of application, were to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace a diſtruſt ſomewhat to neere al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied to deſperation.</p>
            <p>When therefore this infirmity ſhall <note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> happen, and proceede of the cauſes before-ſaid (which is eaſie to be known by argument, and the characters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:2092:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
mentioned (I would haue you the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> carefully to rub and chafe the childes head co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually with warme cloathes, and to keepe it in a temperate warme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Then take Eyebright (or red Sage if you cannot get Eyebright) Wood-Bettony, or Garden Bettony, Fenel (or Fenell-ſeed) and of the Fenel or Fenel-ſeed a double quantity to either of the other two; ſtamp them &amp; ſtraine them, then infuſe them in ſtrong Ale, as to a quart or three pints of Ale, one ſmall handfull of Eyebright or Bettony, and a double quantity of the Fenell: and of this let the Nurſe drinke for the ſpace of twenty, or foure and twenty dayes together, and if it be too ſtrong for her, let her alay and temper it with fine Sugar or well clarified honey, and doubtleſſe (by Gods permiſſion) if any helpe at all be left in Nature, this will reſtore it, otherwiſe the expence of greater charges will be but the loſſe of your further labour. And herein by the way let me aduiſe you to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber
<pb facs="tcp:2092:8"/>
to gather theſe hearbs (if it be poſſible) in May or Iune, &amp; hauing dried them in the ſhadow, preſerue them for your vſe all the yeare following, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing occaſion to vſe them, beat them in a Morter to fine pouder, then ſearſe it, &amp; <note place="margin">A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to one draught of new Ale, infuſe of each of theſe ſeueral powders as much as you can well take vpon a ſixe pence; but of the Fenell a better quantity, all being compounded together. Now if you haue not the hearbs prouided at this eſpeciall ſeaſon, then know that in caſe of extremity, you may gather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at any time, &amp; vſe them as was firſt of all preſcribed, at leaſt euery morning and euening if not at other houres.</p>
            <p>And herein is an excellent obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be obſerued, that the vnskilfull practitioners in this Art (who taking theſe deſperate cures in hand) and not looking to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tendernes &amp; delicacie of the eie, wil only apply ſharp medicines (cauſing a torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; pain wher no pain is neceſſary) which is not only co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary
<pb facs="tcp:2092:9"/>
to the charitable rules of Art, but vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly offenſiue to all good mindes to behold any creature (eſpecially weake Infants) ſo vnmercifully afflicted by theſe vnskilfull and hard-hearted tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentors, and ſo much the rather, in as much as their cruelty is extended vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the eye, being a member moſt quicke, &amp; of greateſt ſence and feeling.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 2. <hi>Of Cataracks in the eies, their diuers kinds, ſignes cure and preuentions.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAuing ſhewed the imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons generally happening vnto Infants, with their preuentions and cures, I will now proceede to the more ſubſtantiall diſeaſes of the eyes, and ſuch as indeede are incident to all people of all ages, of which the moſt principall and moſt dangerous is that <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which is called the Catarack, being a thicke, ſlymie and tough filme, bred and ingendred foure elements within
<pb facs="tcp:2092:9"/>
the eye, eyther naturally by the fluxe of groſſe and euill humors, or acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally by the means of ſome ſtroke, bruſe or wipe vpon the eye, by which the member being offended, puts forth that ill and naughty ſubſtance, whereby the ſight is not onely hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and impaired, but alſo wholely ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, and depriued of all worthy vſe and benefit.</p>
            <p>To ſpeake then generally of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharack, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> you ſhall vnderſtand that there be ſixe ſeuerall kindes thereof, as firſt the hazell coloured Catharack, the Catharack of the colour of the skie, the grayiſh Catharack, the blacke Catharack, the white Catha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rack, and the yellowiſh greene Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharack; and of theſe the three firſt are curable, and the latter three vtterly incurable.</p>
            <p>Now for as much as there may be a <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> failing in the true knowledge, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning of theſe Catharacks, that you may be better enabled to iudge which
<pb facs="tcp:2092:10"/>
is curable and which is incurable; you ſhall vnderſtand, that if the Patient grieued with any of theſe Catharacks, ſhall be able to diſcerne or perceiue the glimmering or ſhining, either of the Sunne, fire, flame or candle-light, that then queſtionleſſe all ſuch Catha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racks are curable, and by Art to be holpen (the Practicioner hauing knowledge in the ſame) but if he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſcerne any ſuch brightneſſe, and that all things ſeeme blacke, clowdie, and without any apprehenſion of ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then be aſſured that all ſuch are vtterly incurable, and a man may both ſaue the conſumption of his purſe, and the torment of his body.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe which are curable, they <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> are to be cured by the Catharack nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, the demonſtration of which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>edleſſe here to be expreſt; becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Artiſt or Profeſſour in this Art, ought or ſhould be ignorant in the true vſe thereof, and to ſet downe in imperfect words, a thing of ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite
<pb facs="tcp:2092:10"/>
perfection, whereby ignorance may be imboldened to aduenture on that which is farre beyond his cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, were to giue courage to that from which my vttermoſt endeuours doe daily ſeeke to diſſwade them, and therefore let euery good man be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full not to meddle with the needle, till experience and long practiſe in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of like nature, haue made him an abſolute Maſter in the true vſe of the needle.</p>
            <p>After the Catharack is couched, or taken away with the needle (by a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Practicioner) the Patient muſt be exceeding carefull of himſelfe, that by no meanes hee take any colde, for the leaſt colde which ſhall enforce him to ſneeſe, cough, or otherwiſe to ſtraine any of the opticke nerues or members, will ſodainly make the Catharact to riſe againe, and ſo bring on a miſchiefe much greater then at the beginning; and therefore by all meanes the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent muſt be contented to lye muffed
<pb facs="tcp:2092:11"/>
and warme for eight or nine dayes, till all ſuch danger be auoyded.</p>
            <p>Now for the preuention of theſe Catharacks, that they may either not grow at all, or beginning to grow, that they may be taken away long ere they come to any dangerous iſſue, as alſo to preuent both the danger and torment, which cannot but neceſſarily depend vpon the vſe of the needle; I would wiſh all ſorts of perſons of what ſexe or age ſo euer, whether old, young, or of middle eſtate, as ſoone as they ſhall perceiue their ſights to decline or grow dimme without any paine, or much extraordinary wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, then to vſe this powder hereafter following, in ſuch ſort as you ſhall finde it preſcribed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:2092:11"/>
            <head>CHAP. 3. <hi>An approoued and moſt excellent receite both for the cure and preuention, of all ſorts of Catharacks of what nature ſo euer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO cure the Catharack of what nature ſo euer, which beginneth to grow, or to preuent the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing or blindneſſe, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes from the ſame; as ſoone as you ſhall perceiue the firſt offence, vſe this drinke, and be ſure you ſhall finde the vertue and great perfection thereof: for it will not onely take away miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe bred, but preuent the breeding and growth of miſchiefe; and if caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty happen not, doubtleſſe olde age may bring a cleare ſight to the laſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute; for it not onely giueth ſtrength to the weake eye, whether the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe proceede from any defect of the braine, or other diſturbance of humor or inflamation, but alſo fortifieth it
<pb facs="tcp:2092:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
againſt all other infirmity, which may any way annoy or trouble it, as my daily experience hath found to my owne particular ſatisfaction, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good mens comforts: the ſubſtance of which excellent receit, is this which followeth: Take of the powder before rehearſed in the firſt Chapter, and in ſuch manner prepared and gathered as is there ſpoken, together with the houres, times, and quantities, as is there ſet downe, onely with this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that whereas there the Nurſe is appointed to vſe it for the benefit of the childe (the medicine working from a ſecondary meanes, as from the milke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which the Infant ſucketh) here the party muſt as the Nurſe vſe it him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for his owne profit, and not faile but morning and euening to take it, and the newer that the drinke is (in which the powder is infuſed) the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is, for it will enforce a man ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to belch and breake winde vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, which is much anailing in this
<pb facs="tcp:2092:12"/>
cure, becauſe the aſcending of the fume purgeth and worketh great ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in the eyes, which the rather to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, you ſhall when the fume and winde ariſeth, keepe your mouth cloſe, and with your fingers ſtop your noſthrils, that as neere as you can the whole fume may aſſend into the head and eyes: whereby it comes that your newe Ale or bottell Ale is thought moſt ſoueraine to be vſed with this powder: but where neither bottel Ale nor new Ale is to be gotten, if then you vſe to eate the ſame quantity of powder (before rehearſed) dry with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any moyſture, it is alſo very auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Neither muſt you faile morning nor euening after the taking of this powder (whether dry or in drinke) but to walke at leaſt an houre after vp and downe, that the medicine may worke both the ſooner, the better, and with more efficacie, neither neede this walking vp and downe be limitted to any certaine place of ſpeciall retiring,
<pb facs="tcp:2092:13"/>
but may very well ſerue for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of any outward or inward bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, as your affaires ſhall moue you: neither neede you to ſtand too ſtrictly vpon the quantity, but after the vſe of it a little ſpace, then either to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe or diminiſh the quantity, as you ſhall finde your ſtomack apt, and able to receiue it.</p>
            <p>Some may imagine becauſe theſe ſimples are ſo little curious, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they may carrie but little vertue: but let not ſuch folly deceiue thee, for they are all of moſt ſingular worth and vertue, eſpecially for the eyes, in ſo much that the Auncients affirme, that the Serpent which is the ſubtilleſt and wiſeſt of all creatures, as ſoone as hee waxeth olde, and findes his ſight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to faile him, preſently he goes to the roote of the Fenell, or to the leafe, according to the ſeaſon, and eate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, hee findes preſent eaſe and redreſſe of his infirmity. And of like nature is your Bettony and the
<pb facs="tcp:2092:13"/>
reſt, ſo that no penne can write too much of their vertue, nor any tongue too highly extoll the praiſe of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent compound, being vſed in ſuch ſort as is already preſcribed, for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the abuſe of any thing turnes the greateſt vertue to the greateſt viciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And thus much of the Catha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racks and their cure.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 4. <hi>Of accidentall wounds in the eyes by what meanes ſo euer, and of the cure thereof.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAuing ſpoken of Catharacks whether naturall or accidentall, and of the cures thereof, I will now proceede to other accidentall wounds or hurts in the eyes, as are pricks with thornes, kniues, needles, or any other ſharpe-pointed inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſtrokes with the eares of cornes, ſtubble, bryers, or any other bruiſe or wipe in the eye, which when at any time they ſhall happen, be moſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
<pb facs="tcp:2092:14"/>
carefull (of what age or ſexe ſo euer thou be, whether young or olde) not to apply any ſharpe or coroding medicine thereunto, either waters, powders, or other compounds which are of hot, fretting and ſharpe nature: but rather follow mine aduiſe herein, and as ſoone as you ſhall receiue any of theſe miſchances, preſently get one of wholeſome and ſweet breath to blow into your eye, to coole and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwage the paine thereof (for much good ſhall be found thereby) and be ſure that the party ſo blowing, haue not eaten Garlick, or taken Tobacco any ſmall ſpace before, for they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame and make hot the breath, and ſo aſſwage not but encreaſe your tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereas it ſhould bee coole, ſweet, and wholeſome breath, which ſhould mollifie and make leſſe the paine you ſuffer; this done, take the white of an egge, and beate it to oyle, and dipping fine round pleagants of flaxe or ſoft towe therein, as broad as
<pb facs="tcp:2092:14"/>
an Engliſh ſhilling; apply it to the wounded eye, and renue it as it drieth, and this will not onely draw away the corrupt or bruſed blood, but alſo cleanſe and coole the eye in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that the cure will be made more ſafe and quickly; or if this cannot be had, take Parſly and ſweet butter, and beate and mixe them well together, and ſo apply them to the eye, and it will worke the ſame effect as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, whereas to apply any ſharper me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, whether water or powder, it is great ods that you not onely looſe that which is already wounded, but alſo periſh the ſound one alſo, and ſo looſe the benefit, of the moſt comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableſt ſence which man enioyeth. If this aſſwage not the paine, and giue caſe according to your expectation, then take white-bread crummes finely grated, and of the beſt new milke, and boyle them together till they be thick, then apply it to the eye luke-warme, and ſo renue it once in ſixe or eight
<pb facs="tcp:2092:15"/>
houres at the firſt dreſſing, and after in tenne or twelue houres, as the eye ſhall amend, and there is no doubt but the cure will ſoone be brought to that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which your owne heart can deſire.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 5. <hi>Of red furious eyes, which are troubled with a hot ſcalding rhewme, the cauſe, offences, and the cure.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NExt to theſe accidental wounds in eyes, we will proceede to the red furious eye, which is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a ſharpe, ſcalding, and fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting rhewme, ouerflowing and annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame. And here you ſhall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that for theſe eyes in diuers caſes, there are good &amp; certaine cures to be wrought, eſpecially if you haue a good Practicioner in the ſame: But now a-dayes there are ſo many wilfull and vnskilfull dealers with this Art, that many by their ignorance are
<pb facs="tcp:2092:15"/>
made blinde, which otherwiſe might enioy the benefit of their ſight to their liues end, nor doth this blindneſſe fall vpon them as the Parrot climbes <hi>(lento pede)</hi> by leaſure or with ſlow ſteps, but ſodainly and quickly, as within two or three houres or little more at the vttermoſt, which that you may the better perceiue, and thereby the better auoyde their ignorance, I will by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſhew you how many vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Patients are made blinde.</p>
            <p>Firſt, when the grieued Patient comes to the vnskilfull Practitioner, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and deſires his helpe, preſently (igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance being his guide) he opens a veine in the temples of his head, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther veine vnder the eye, cloſe by the noſe, and alſo a third in the roofe of the mouth, or vnder the tongue, which blood is no ſooner taken away, but preſently blindneſſe inſueth, as hath beene experienced by diuers, as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a yong Gentlewoman of little Sno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge in Norfolke, and one <hi>Iames Feyld</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2092:16"/>
of Broughton in Huntington Shiere, both which, after the taking of their blood, fell inſtantly blinde within two houres after, albeit both their ſights were reaſonable good before, onely afflicted with ſome little paine, and the ſuſpition of dimneſſe, nor was the blood which was taken from the latter much; for it was no more then was receiued into two little cupping-glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes placed on his necke, and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding preſently he fell blinde, nor could euer after be cured: and in like ſort vnto theſe, one Goodman <hi>Fletcher,</hi> dwelling in a little Towne neere Bourne in Lincolne Shiere, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſome ſmall impediment in his eyes, and comming to an ignorant Practicioner, had a veine opened in his temples, and another by his noſe, but the blood was no ſooner receiued, when as the ſight was vtterly loſt for euer. And as theſe, I could cite a world of others, were not the circumſtances too tedious, and the rehearſall need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:2092:16"/>
for our preſent purpoſe; onely this I collect from theſe inſtances, that euery man troubled with theſe infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, ſhould be exceeding carefull in making election of his Artiſt: and euery Artiſt religiouſly carefull not to exceede his knowledge, or meddle with the taking away of blood, or weakening the eye by any applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then which there cannot be a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter miſchiefe; for aſſuredly all theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euitable blindneſſes happening to the parties before recited, might haue beene auoyded, and the ſight certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly both fortified and preſerued, had they vſed the meanes onely which here I will ſet downe, without any other aditions of greater torment.</p>
            <p>Whoſoeuer therefore ſhal be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in his eyes with the infirmities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid, I would firſt wiſh him either by his owne dyet, or the counſaile of the learned Phyſitian to keepe his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſoluble: Then take of white Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peris, and of Bolearmoniack, of each
<pb facs="tcp:2092:17"/>
the quantity of a good French Peaſe, and beate them to very fine powder, then take of raine water (if it may be got) or ſnow water; or for want of them fine cleare running water, the quantity of a quarter of a pint, and put it into a glaſſe violl ſuteable to the quantity, and then adde to it the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Coporis and Bolearmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack, and ſhake and mixe them very well together till they be incorporate, then dipping a fine feather in this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, waſh your eyes therewith mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening, if your occaſions draw you not abroad into the ayre, for then it will offend and make your eyes ſmart too violently, ſo that in that caſe when you muſt trauaile, you may then ſpare your morning dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, but by no meanes the euening when you goe to reſt. Now if at the firſt dreſſing you finde the water be too ſharpe and biting, ſo as you can hardly endure the torment, then you ſhall alay it by adding to a little more
<pb facs="tcp:2092:17"/>
water, or a little more of the Bolear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniack, prouided that you make it not too gentle, for to take away all ſence of ſmarting, is to take away all force, and ſtrength of vertue.</p>
            <p>Now for as much as not any of theſe eyes thus afflicted with theſe ſharpe &amp; ſcalding rhewmes, are voyde of much ſoreneſſe, rawneſſe, and bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe about the lids and cloſures of the eyes, and eſpecially at the two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treameſt corners of the ſame, It ſhall therefore be meete for you for the cure of the ſame, to take of the thickeſt and beſt Creame you can get, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmeare and ſpread it all ouer the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of a copper or braſſe Panne, Ket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, or Baſon, leauing it of a very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable thinneſſe: then take another veſſell of little leſſe quantity, and fill it full of ſtrong new made vrine or chamber-lie; then take the braſſe veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell in which the Creame is ſpread, and whelme it ouer the vrine (yet ſo as it may not touch the vrine) and let it
<pb facs="tcp:2092:18"/>
there reſt the ſpace of nine or tenne dayes, then take it off and gather the Creame from the bottome of the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and putit into a glaſſe, and keepe it cloſe; with this oyntment, anoynt all the rawe places of the eye lids eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry night when you goe to bed, and it will not onely take away the rawneſſe and ſmarting, but alſo dry them vp and skinne them: and herein you muſt obſerue to let the oyntment come as little into your eye as is poſſible, for it wil cauſe ſmarting, thogh otherwiſe it doth not further hurt. And thus much of the red furious eye, which is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a hot ſcalding rhewme.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 6. <hi>Of the red fierie eye, which is oppreſt with groſſe humors, and accompanied with a corrupt breath.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THere is another ſort of red eyes, which are full of contagion and groſſe humors, and though not
<pb facs="tcp:2092:18"/>
altogether ſo moyſt as the former, yet fully as painefull and troubleſome; for the inflamation is more violent, and the rhewme almoſt as ſharpe. Theſe kinde of ſore eyes are very curious to be healed, for the party that is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled therewith, hath euer for the moſt part a very ſtrong and corrupt breath, which is ſo nouriſhed and fed by the euill humors that accompany the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, that it is very difficult, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth both much Art and care in the reformation.</p>
            <p>Hee therefore that is troubled with <note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> theſe enflamed fierie and corrupt eyes, let him firſt purge his body well, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with purgation, glyſter, or vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite, according to the abillity of the party which is diſeaſed, and in this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Phyſicke, I doe aduiſe euery man that is carefull of the health of his owne body, not to take any but by the aduiſe either of the reuerend Doctor or learned Phyſitian, and not to relie on the audacious boldneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:2092:19"/>
of ignorant Profeſſours, for in theſe dayes there are a world of <hi>Empericks</hi> and <hi>Mountebanks,</hi> which will take vpon them to giue Phyſick, whoſe skill (God knowes) can neither diſcerne nor iudge the true nature of the moſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie ſimples; therefore let euery man that loues himſelfe, flie to the protection of the beſt, for it is beſt cheape, and brings with it the beſt ſafety; for none are more coſtly then the ignorant, becauſe they hold great gaine a great aduancement to their glory and reputation, reckoning not with the good they haue done, but the profit they haue receiued.</p>
            <p>There are another ſort of Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, who becauſe they haue ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight in ſome of the liberall Arts, think they may as liberally deale with this particular Art, and thereupon will vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to giue Phyſick, yet not for your money but vertues ſake (as they pretend it) yet when you haue recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with their Apothicaries, and ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:2092:19"/>
vp their billes and extrauagant charges, as a buſhell or two of corne, Hens, Capons, Chickens, and other ſuch like gifts of gratuity (which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but euer accompany a thankfull nature) you will finde that the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile of a truly learned and worthy Phyſitian had beene more eaſie, more cheape, and a million folde more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing for your health and preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Therefore as before I ſaid, after the greeued party hath purged and made cleane his body by the aduiſe of learning and experience, he ſhall then take the water of Copporis and Bole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armoniack, which was at large ſet downe in the former Chapter, and with it dreſſe and waſh his eyes in ſuch ſort (morning and euening) as was there declared, and with the ſame cautions, limits, and obſeruations, as was there expreſſed. And if the eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids (as before ſaid) ſhall grow rawe, ſore, or bleared, he ſhall then with the oyntment of Creame (mentioned in
<pb facs="tcp:2092:20"/>
the laſt Chapter) annoynt them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with in the ſame manner, as hath like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe beene mentioned, without alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or augmentation.</p>
            <p>Now for as much as the diſtilling down of the rhewme into thoſe weake parts of the eyes, is both the greateſt nouriſher of the diſeaſe and infirmity, and alſo the greateſt cauſe of the paine and anguiſh: to ſtay the fluxe thereof, and to make the member more apt, and fitter to receiue cure; you ſhall take halfe a handfull of Bay-ſalt, and ſpreading it before the fire, dry it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly, then hauing a little bagge of linnen cloath ready; put the ſalt ſo dried into the ſame, and being of a reaſonable warmeneſſe, apply it to the nape of the necke in the hollow part, next to the iuncture of the head; and there let it reſt the ſpace of foure and twenty houres, and then renue it, and apply to another in the ſame manner: and thus doe once in foure and twenty houres till eaſe be found, and that the
<pb facs="tcp:2092:20"/>
rhewme ceaſe to oppreſſe you, which queſtionleſſe will quickly be effected, if any true care be taken.</p>
            <p>Againe, for the ſtaying of the rhewme, if you vſe to take of the Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris water (before ſaid) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with waſh your eyes, the temples of your head, and behinde your eares, ſuffering the water to dry in, and not to be wipte away, it is of great vertue and efficacie, for it not onely ſtayeth the rhewme, but is alſo very ſoueraine againſt the head-ake, and all paines of that nature, as tooth-ake and the like; and it ſafely healeth both the watry eye, which ſmarteth ſometimes, and itcheth other ſometime, as alſo all other eyes that are enflamed.</p>
            <p>Now if it ſo fall out (as in great cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and corrupt bodies it may eaſily doe) that theſe things before preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, worke not in all points according to your expectation, then you ſhall for refuge flie to this receite which hereafter followeth, and doubt not
<pb facs="tcp:2092:21"/>
but by the grace of God you ſhall with much ſafety and contentment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riue at the full end of your purpoſe.</p>
            <p>You ſhall take a quarter of an ounce of Cantharides, &amp; lay them to ſteepe in the beſt wine vinegar, for the ſpace of foure or fiue houres; then take yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Treate or greene Treate, or any ſticking plaiſter, and ſpread it on a lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloath plaiſterwiſe, ſo as the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity may be deuided into three plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; then take the Cantharides, and on each plaiſter lay ſome of them, then lay one of the plaiſters to the nape of your necke, and to each wriſt of your arme another, and doe this at night when you goe to bed, taking great care that you binde the plaiſters ſo faſt, that they by no meanes fall away, vntill you remoue them (which would be the next morning) then when you haue taken them off, you ſhall ſee bli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters (which the violence of the ſalue will raiſe) and thoſe you ſhall preſently let out, making the water euacuate,
<pb facs="tcp:2092:21"/>
and with the ſame plaiſter without the Cantharides heale the ſores againe; then vſe the firſt water as afore-ſaid, and no doubt by Gods grace but the cure will be ſoone finiſhed.</p>
            <p>This laſt receite is ſharpe and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and therefore I would not aduiſe any man to vſe it, but onely in caſes of extremity, and where the cure is tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and doubtfull.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 7. <hi>For ſore waterie eyes proceeding of a colde rhewme, or for ſuch as begin to growe darke, and doe euer preſent to the party a double obiect.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THere is another ſort of ſore eyes vvhich proceede of a colde rhewme, &amp; they are beſt knowne by their exceeding much moyſtneſſe and continuall weeping, putting the Patient to no paine more then priuate vexation; it is a diſeaſe of great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and difficulty, and by moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours
<pb facs="tcp:2092:22"/>
of the Art held almoſt incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; yet certes, it ſildome or neuer bringeth blindneſſe, onely the trouble and noyſomneſſe is much worſe then the danger, and therefore I would wiſh euery one in this caſe, not to tamper too much with their eyes, or try the experiment of many medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines; for that may bring blindneſſe perforce, onely I would haue them vſe the bagge of dried ſalt, in ſuch manner as hath beene before declared in the former Chapter, for aſſuredly where it failes, other medicines will but worke other worſe imperfections.</p>
            <p>Now for the other ſort of ſore eyes, which beginning to growe dimme and darke, preſent to the party grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a double obiect; making euery ſingle thing he looks on, appeare as it were two, or a double body; you ſhall for the cure thereof take the powder of Eyebright, Bettony, &amp;c. mentioned in the firſt Chapter, and either drinke it with new Ale, bottell-Ale, or the
<pb facs="tcp:2092:22"/>
like; or elſe eare it dry, as hath beene formerly declared in the third Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with the ſame obſeruations and cautions; and queſtionleſſe there is no doubt of moſt ſpeedy and eaſie cure, as experience hath found out, and I doubt not but all men ſhall finde to their benefit and comfort.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 8. <hi>For the Pin and the Web, and the like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities in eyes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis diſeaſe which is called the Pin and Web in the eyes, are lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle white ſpots in the eyes, which growing in or neere vnto the ſight, doth by proceſſe of time encreaſe and weare away the ſight, leauing the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty altogether blinde and incurable; which to preuent, and take away theſe ſpots ere they come to the height of miſchiefe, you ſhall take a little Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh honey, and a fewe Dazie leaues or rootes (according to the ſeaſon) and
<pb facs="tcp:2092:23"/>
hauing ſtampt and ſtrayned the leaues or rootes, mixe with it the honey, then adde to them a little womans milke, and mixe and incorporate all well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, then at night when you goe to bed; and likewiſe in the morning when you riſe, drop a drop or two thereof into your eyes; and thus doe for the ſpace of a week or thereabouts, and by the grace of God the cure will be finiſhed to your comfort: alſo if to this receite you adde a little of the iuice of the true ground Iuie, which by ſome is called Tunhoofe or Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoofe; you ſhall finde it very auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, eſpecially in great and dangerous cures, for it is more ſharpe and ſtrong then the other, and worketh his ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects with more ſtrength and violence.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:2092:23"/>
            <head>CHAP. 9. <hi>For the imperfections which happen to eies by meanes of the ſmall Pockes, or for eyes that are troubled with wormes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>DIuers imperfections doe happen to the eyes by meanes of the ſmall Pocks, either to olde or young perſons, eſpecially when the maiſter Pock ſetteth in the eye, or in both the eyes (as it often happeneth) for cure whereof many doe vſe to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter ſharpe biting waters, but in ſo doing, they take not away the ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, but the ſight for euer, therefore by no meanes meddle with thoſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roding medicines, but rather vſe theſe gentle receites hereafter mentioned.</p>
            <p>Take a prety quantity of white Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar-candie, or elſe ſome of the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-bolt ſtone, or for want of both a peece of the Cuttell-bone which the Goldſmithes doe vſe, and hauing bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten any of them, and ſearſt it to as fine
<pb facs="tcp:2092:24"/>
a powder as is poſſible; with a ſmall quill blowe ſome of it into the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded eyes, &amp; it is a moſt certaine cure.</p>
            <p>For thoſe eyes which are troubled with little wormes, like thoſe in mens hands but ſmaller, cauſing an extreame itching in the eyes, ſo that ſome rub them with their hands, ſome with clothes, and ſome with a peece of ſilke, all which is both vnwholeſome and offenſiue (for they ſhould not be rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed at all) becauſe any rubbing doth prouoke the rhewme to diſtill and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell to that part: and much touching or handling of the eyes, cauſeth both tenderneſſe and ſoreneſſe; which to preuent and to kill thoſe wormes which annoy you, you ſhall take the Copporis water before mentioned, and with it waſh your eyes morning and euening, and compell your ſelfe to ſneeſe as much as is poſſible, and it is a preſent cure.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:2092:24"/>
            <head>CHAP. 10. <hi>For the filme vpon the eyes, or things of like nature, or for hurts with powder or ſhot.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FOr ſuch eyes as are troubled with filmes or thinne ſcummes, grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſpreading ouer the ſight, you ſhall take the marrow of a Gooſe wing, and Ginger beaten and ſearſt to a very fine powder, and mixe them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well together, then with a quill take vp a good drop thereof, and put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the eye which hath the filme; and thus doe euery morning when you riſe, and euery euening when you goe to bed, or for want of this you may vſe the powder of the thunder-bolt ſtone before ſpoken of, in ſuch manner as hath beene before recited, and it is a cure both ſafe and certaine.</p>
            <p>Now if any man ſhall happen ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſhooting in a Piece, or by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſuall meanes to receiue any hurt
<pb facs="tcp:2092:25"/>
in his eyes, either by the burning of the Gunpowder, or by hauing the ſame blowne into his eyes, or if they be offended with the ruſt of the Peece, ſhiuers or ſuch like, you ſhall preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly get one that hath a good ſight, and a nimble ſtedie hand, and taking a fine quill, make it as ſharpe as a needle, and with the ſame let them picke out the ſpots, cornes, or ſhiuers, and wipe them cleane away with the fine taſſell of a Handkerchiefe, then waſh it with faire running water, and fine Sugar-candy well mixt together, and dropt gently into the eye, and the cure will ſoone be finiſhed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 12. <hi>For certaine particular wounds in the eyes, as with dore latches, cudgels, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IF any man of what age or degree ſo euer, ſhall by going in the darke, or other caſualty, ruſh vpon the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of dores, bolts, nailes, or the like,
<pb facs="tcp:2092:25"/>
or by thruſts with cudgels, foyles, or blowes with cat goe far, thorn, billets, or the like, receiue any blow or ſtripe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the eye, or haue the eye-ball thruſt out, ſo that it lye vpon the cheeke; you ſhall then firſt put vp the eye into the place, where before it was; and doe it with great lenitie and gentleneſſe, then with a cloath ſtay the eye ſo pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for the ſpace of two or three houres; then take whitebread crums finely grated and new milk, and ſeethe it till it be thick, and ſo apply it warme to the eye; or for want of it Parſly and Butter, as hath beene before declared; but by no meanes any ſharpe waters, or ſmarting medicine, and the cure will in few dayes be finiſhed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:2092:26"/>
            <head>CHAP. 12. <hi>Of weake eyes, and the cauſes of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining, the helpes and preuentions.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe ſight is weakned two wayes, that is to ſay, either naturally, or accidentally; if naturally, it is by meanes of olde age, weakeneſſe of the braine, or elſe by the ouer-flowing of groſſe and vnwholeſome humors, if accidentally, then it is by the meanes of ill diet; the vſe of naughty applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, diſorder in exerciſe, wounds, ruſhes, bruſes, and the like.</p>
            <p>Now that you may know when your ſight declineth &amp; waxeth weake, <note place="margin">whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> obſerue euer that when you ſee better farre off then neere hand (as when you looke on a booke or the like) that then your ſight beginneth to wayne, alſo ſuch eyes as doe neuer runne, but are alwayes dry, they are weake eyes, and very ſubiect to Catharacks: againe, if the eyes be cleare as glaſſe, but yet troubled, and that the ſight of the eye
<pb facs="tcp:2092:26"/>
doth ſhake and quiuer like the needle of a Diall, holding a continuall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without ceaſing, ſuch an eye is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a weake eye, and declining.</p>
            <p>Now for the cure of any of theſe imperfections (for they are all natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall) there is nothing more ſoueraine then the powder mentioned in the firſt Chapter, being prepared and vſed as is there ſet downe.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe weakeneſſes which come by accident, they are euer to be cured by their contrary, as if any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede by ryot and diſorder, they muſt be amended by temperance, if by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent labor, then by moderate exerciſe: if by ill applications, then by whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome receites, and if by wounds, then by wholeſom ſalues, to any of which if you adde the benefit of the Coporis water before ſpecified, the cure will be much ſooner finiſhed.</p>
            <p>Now beſides theſe defects already ſpoken of, there is another as groſſe as any, and exceeding frequent amongſt
<pb facs="tcp:2092:27"/>
all young wiues, maydes, and women of each degree and quality, and that is the wearing of Maſtick patches or plaiſters on the temples of their heads; which howſoeuer pride for faſhion ſake, or care for health ſake doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, yet can nothing be more hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or noyſome: ſome will ſay they weare them for the head-ake; ſome for the tooth-ake: yet I affirme except your eyes be too exceeding moyſt and dropping, you cannot vſe any thing more hurtfull; for if the eye bee dry and doe not water, then the ſtaying of that comfortable moyſture which ſhould quicken the eye, weakens it and the ſtrength being taken away which ſhould preſerue it, there doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Diſeaſe but Blindnes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let this my Caueat warne you if you will preſerue good fights, to caſt away thoſe playſters, and in ſteade thereof onely take running water and waſh the temples of your head there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and behinde your eares, and
<pb facs="tcp:2092:27"/>
wipe not the water away but let it dry of it ſelfe and thus doing euery mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, it will take away all head-ake and tooth-ake, and ſtay the Rewme and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther griefes, for which your Maſticke patches, and Gumme playſters were vſed; for beleeue me it neither addeth Beauty to the face, nor health to the Body, but on the contrary taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all ſtrength from the eyes and bringeth blindnes euer too earely, as I haue found by experience, and for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter proofe I will repeate vnto you one true inſtance.</p>
            <p>There was a young woman dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in <hi>Downham</hi> in Norfolke, which was troubled much with the head-ake, and ſending for aduice (as ſhe thought to the skilfull) was directed to take one of theſe plaiſters, and to weare it on her temples, but preſently it tooke away her ſight in fewe houres after, yet it cured her head-ake, now if this plaiſter had beene applied to the nape of the necke, and not to the temples,
<pb facs="tcp:2092:28"/>
it had preuailed, and no euill had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued. The plaiſter which ſhe applied was compounded of wine vinegar, a Roſe-cake, an egge roſted hard, and Commin-ſeede; all which ingredience are good if they had beene applied to the right place; but being miſplaced on the temples, it drew away the ſtrength of the eyes, and brought blindneſſe. Therefore I aduiſe euery <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> one that is troubled with the head-ake or the like, onely to take a little ſtrong wine vinegar, and a little oyle of Spike, and to mixe them very well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and then to bathe therewith thoſe parts where the paine is, and it will not onely giue eaſe to the paine, but alſo adde ſtrength and comfort to the eyes, as I haue found by moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and infallible experience.</p>
            <p>There is another defect to which I muſt giue a great <hi>Caueat,</hi> and eſpecially to all you Schoolemaſters &amp; Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtreſſes which haue the charge of young Children, bee they Boyes or
<pb facs="tcp:2092:28"/>
gyrles; that in any caſe you obſerue and note well the ſtrength or weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of your Schollers eyes: and where you finde imperfection or imbecillitie in the ſight, there by all meanes to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from forcing them to looke on very ſmall Prints, or to ſowe on very fine Samplers, or in curious workes, eſpecially blacke workes, for they are not onely hurtfull and bring ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding much weaknes to the eyes, but alſo the more they ſtriue and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to beholde the obiect they looke on, the more hurt they doe to their eyes, and the weaker their ſight groweth, Therefore in theſe caſes where you ſee ſuch weake ſights be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides reforming the faults before ſaid, you muſt prouide for them large brim'd Hats to ſhade their eyes, for they haue not any greater enemy then the light: and alſo you muſt giue them of the Powder (mentioned in the firſt Chapter) to drinke in ſuch ſorte as is there preſcribed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:2092:29"/>
            <head>CHAP. 12. <hi>An excellent and approued Cure for any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamation in the face, for the Corny face, the Rich face, and the like.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHoſoeuer is troubled with any inflamation in his face, whether it bee plaine red which is heate, or pumples and red pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuls which is corny or vniuerſally o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all the face pimples and puſtuls both red and purple, which is called the rich face; let him knowe that all ſuch inflamations, beſides the noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomnes and vnſeemelineſſe thereof, it is alſo hurtfull and troubleſome to the ſight, therefore for the Cure of ſuch an Infirmity, let him take running wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and roch Allome, and put them together into a Glaſſe or violl, and by ſhaking and toſſing, ſymbolize and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate them ſo as the Allome may be waſted, then at night when you goe to bed, take a fine Napkin and wet it in
<pb facs="tcp:2092:29"/>
the water well and apply it to your face, and let it there lye till the water ſoake in and dry on your face, and then renew it, and doe thus as oft as you ſhall thinke good; and with all ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine (aſmuch as you can) from ſtrong drinkes and hote Wines, and the cure will be more ſpeedy; Now if the cure proue ſlowe, you ſhall take of Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, of large Mace, of Gooſe-greaſe or Capons-greaſe, of each alike, and mixe and temper them well together, then put them into a gally pot and with this oyntment, annoynt your face as oft as you ſhall thinke good, and doubt not but the cure will be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpeedy and certaine: but if you find that this inflamation proceedeth from the liuor onely; if then beſides theſe outward applications before ſaid, you take the aduice of a learned Phyſitian, and now and then purge your body, there is no doubt but your face will be as cleare and well complectioned as it was before.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="caveat">
            <pb facs="tcp:2092:30"/>
            <head>A caueat to all ſorts of people for the trueſt vſe of the <hi>powder, and drinke mentioned in the firſt Chapter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FOr as much as the powder compounded of Eyebright (or for want of it red Sage) of wood Bettony (or for want of it the garden Bettony) and of Fenell or Fenell-ſeede, in ſuch manner as is at large ſet downe in the firſt Chapter, is of ſuch excellent vſe and vertue, that a man cannot ſpeake too much of it; nor be too carefull to inſtruct how to apply it (whether it be for weake eyes, ſore eyes, dimme eyes, or decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſight whatſoeuer) I thought good therefore to conclude this my ſmall Treatiſe with this Caueat, that whoſoeuer ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:2092:30"/>
haue occaſion to vſe this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, they may freely chuſe whether they will vſe the powder in ſuch ſort, as is ſhewed in the firſt chapter, or elſe take the hearbs greene, and infuſe them in Ale, in ſuch ſort, as is ſhewed before for the Nurſe in the firſt Chapter al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, prouided that they faile not to continue the vſe of this drinke, for the full ſpace of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or foure and twenty dayes at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then after at pleaſure.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="byline">
            <pb facs="tcp:2092:31"/>
            <p>Written by <hi>Richard Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brooke,</hi> Practicioner in the Art of the Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, and dwelling in <hi>Kings-Linne</hi> in Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke. 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:2092:31"/>
            <head>A Table of all the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall things contayned in this Booke.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>OF blindneſſe both curable and incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in Infants, the cauſe, preuention and cure.</cell>
                     <cell>Chap. 1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The ſoueraine powder.</cell>
                     <cell>ibid.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Of Catharacks in the eyes, their diuers kindes, ſignes, cure and preuention.</cell>
                     <cell>Chap. 2.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>An approued receite for the cure of all ſorts of Catharacks of what nature ſoeuer.</cell>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Of accidentall wounds in the eyes by what meanes ſo euer, and of the cure thereof.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Of red furious eyes which are troubled with a hot ſcalding rhewme, the cauſe, offences, and cure.</cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Of the red fierie eye, which is oppreſt with groſſe humors, and accompanied with a corrupt breath.</cell>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>For ſore waterie eyes proceeding of a colde rhewme, or for ſuch as begin to grow darke, and doe euer preſent to the party a double obiect.</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>For the Pin and the Web, and the like infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
